A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office: National Governor's Association of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1993
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Policy Office: National Governor's Association of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1993
The Library of Virginia
35539
1.05 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1990-1994: Wilder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder on 31 October 1996.
Biographical Information
Lawrence Douglas Wilder was born in Richmond, Va., on January 17, 1931. He graduated from Virginia Union University in 1951 and afterwards was drafted into the Army, where he served in the Korean War from 1952-1953 and received a bronze star. He then attended the Howard University School of Law and graduated in 1959. Douglas Wilder was elected to the Virginia Senate in 1969 as the first African American member since Reconstruction and served in the Senate for five terms. In 1985, he was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor as the first African American to be elected to statewide office in Virginia. L. Douglas Wilder won the election for Governor of Virginia in 1989 and served from January 13, 1990 to January 14, 1994. He was the first African American to be elected as Governor in United States.
During the Wilder Administration, the Policy Office was headed by Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, and four Special Assistants: Richard Taylor (Health and Human Resources, and Education), Robert Blue (Finance and Natural Resources), Jeff Nuechterlein (Economic Development and Transportation), and Lynne Porfiri (Administration and Public Safety). The Policy Office was responsible for review and coordination of all policy matters, including: review of proposed legislation from agencies and Cabinet; formulation of the Governor's legislative initiatives; tracking legislation and serving as legislative liaison; review of General Assembly approved legislation submitted to the Governor for signature, amendment or veto; review of death penalty clemency requests, as well as other pardon and restoration of rights requests; review of legal settlements and other legal matters from the Office of the Attorney General's Office; review of proposed regulations; review of all matters pertaining to the judiciary and writs of habeas corpus; review of proposed executive orders; assistance with speech writing; serving as staff for Governor's special commissions; administrative support for Governor's Fellows program; serving as special interest liaison; acting as in-house counsel; and all correspondence with policy implications or pertaining to sensitive or controversial issues requiring legal overview.
Scope and Content
Records of the Policy Office: National Governor's Association, 1990-1993, including agendas, briefing books, brochures, committee notes and reports, correspondence, memorandum, newsletters, programs, publications, testimonies, and other materials. This series documents Governor Wilder's participation in the National Governor's Association, a bipartisan organization of the nation's Governors.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Annual meeting, Briefing Book, 1990 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual meeting, Briefing Book, 1990 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual meeting, Briefing Book, 1991 February (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Annual meeting, 1992 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brochure, Families First with Bill Moyers 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brochure, Strategic Investment Tough Choices for America's Future, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Committee, Agriculture and Rural Development, 1991 July (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committee, Economic Development and Technological Innovation, 1992 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Committee, Finance, Sub-Committee on Health for Families and the Uninsured, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Committee, Finance, Sub-Committee on Social Security and Family Policy, Child Support Enforcement, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Committee, Human Resources (Earned Income Credit), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Committee, International Trade and Foreign Relations, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Committee, Justice and Public Safety Chairman, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Committee Listings for Governors, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Education Program, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Fiscal Survey of States, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Governor's Bulletin Newsletters, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Memorandums, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Memorandum to Staff Advisory Council Members, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- National Conference on Youth Gangs and Violent Juvenile Crime, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Guard and National Defense Policy, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Natural Resources Group, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Policy, Changes and Resolutions in Committees, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Policy, Statements, Proposals, and Positions, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Policy, Statements, Summaries of and Recommendations, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Publication, Policy Positions (1989-1990), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Report, A Healthy America the Challenge for States, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Report, A World of Difference, Report on the Task Force of Global Climate Change, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Report, Curbing Climate Change through State Initiatives, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Report, From Rhetoric to Action State Progress in Restructuring the Education System, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Report, Promoting Quality Businesses: A State Action Agenda, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Report, The State of the States' Environmental Planning, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Russian Winter Campaign, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- State and Local Legal Center, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Strategic Planning Task Force, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Transportation Issues, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Virginia as a Host State, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)